We had dealt with classes last
week and then towards the end
especially with
inheritance between classes.
The last slide on this was
this slide with such artificial classes,
where it was
about structural restrictions.
So that
certain kinds of
inheritance relationships should
not be allowed.
And that was independent of the content of
the classes, that's why those were such artificial names.
Now we want to
deal with content structuring instead.
Therefore now also
more concrete examples.
Here is a constellation, where we have a
class "car" and several classes inherit from it.
This picture here with the converging
arrows or strokes, which then all end
in an inheritance arrow towards
Auto, is equivalent to simply
having such an inheritance
arrow here four times each.
There's nothing
cyclic here.
So structurally,
that's fine.
And even though we haven't
specified attributes and methods now
(I left the
boxes blank in each
case), we can reason from the
names that these may be meaningful relationships.
So we don't look at what happens
to the attributes or methods in inheritance,
but just consider this basic
requirement that inheritance should always be
a true
generalization/specialization relationship.
So we should let other
class inherit from "car" if
representatives of these other
classes are also cars.
A private car is also a
car, just a more specialized car.
A diesel car is also a
car, just a more special car, etc.
That's why, in terms of
content, these are meaningful inheritance relationships.
Each of these four
subclasses is a meaningful
specialization of
the general concept.
We can let
that stand for now.
Interestingly, if you look
at the content here, different
aspects have led
to the specialization.
Certainly, all these four special types
of cars are special manifestations of
cars, but for different
reasons and in different respects.
If you take a look at these four
types of special cars, you will see that, for
example, the two on the left, private
car and diesel car, are both special cars.
But somehow in different ways they
are more special than general cars.
The private car is
more special in terms of
ownership than an
unknown general car:
Who owns
this car?
While diesel car is also a
special car, but specialized in another direction.
That is, not in terms of
ownership, but in terms of propulsion.
That is, private car and diesel
car are different kinds of cars,
but not in the sense that they
could be seen in contrast with each other.
So private cars are not
the opposite of diesel cars,
nor do they contrast with each other
in any other respect, so to speak.
They are just
completely different dimensions
in which a
car can be specialized.
The example is chosen so that this would not
now be the case for all pairings of subclasses.
For example, "private car" and
"company car" are actually not only
more specialized cars, but also
specialized along the same dimension.
Private car and company car are actually in this
sense a pair of opposites, a pair of contrasts.
Different from private
car and diesel car.
And the same is true
for diesel car and solar car.
They too are different kinds of
special cars, but somehow they have
become specialized in the same respect,
namely in terms of their propulsion.
Which again would not apply
to company car and solar car.
Those are specialized
cars for different reasons.
So somehow private car/company car seem
to go together in a sense as
a direction in which a
car can become more specialized.
And diesel car/solar car
also seem to kind
of belong together in that sense
as a way to specialize "car."
And this observation can also
be represented in the diagram.
So represent it in such a way that it
becomes clear that private car and company car are more
specialized cars in one respect, and diesel car/solar
car are more specialized cars in another respect.
Instead of just having all four inherit from
car side by side here, you could group
these subclasses into
groups, so-called generalization groups.
So these
individual generalization
relationships, which were four on the
previous slide, you would group them together.
This could then look
like this, for example:
We still have the
car as the central class.
Also as the top class, which is inherited from,
but which itself does not inherit from anything else.
And we still have
the four subclasses, which
each inherit once from "car" via these
arrows here and once via these arrows here.
But we've summarized that these
two form a group, that
is, a special kind of
inheritance or special expression of cars.
And have even noted here in
what respect (I had said earlier
"ownership", I could have just
said "the status of the car"):
Is it a private
car or a company car?
That would be
one way of specializing.
And diesel car/solar car
are also both subclasses of
"car", but they are grouped here in such
a way that you can see that they
are specialized according to a specific
criterion, namely the criterion of propulsion.
Each group, once the group
and once the group, sort
of subdivides the set of cars
as a whole in different ways.
Of course, this could be important in
an application that is to be modeled.
Because for instance in different parts
of the application simply different generalization
groups are relevant and then
also object instances of other generalization
groups do not
appear at all.
So if we somehow model cars for the
vehicles of a company, then perhaps the distinction
between private and company cars is
relevant for the accounting of this company.
Because it has to deal with it in a
different way from a tax point of view, depending
on the status of
a car that is used.
While for other aspects, such
as the company's ecological balance
sheet, it is perhaps more important to
differentiate between cars according to their drive system.
And therefore, in a certain part of the
application, the status may not be relevant at all.
And then perhaps only instances
of this type would occur there.
In order to be able to distinguish this,
and to be able to give the child
a name, so to speak, a name
is somehow annotated here in each case at
this summarized
inheritance branching.
Directly in the diagram, a meaningful
name of the respective generalization group.
You can even do this if
there is only one specialization type.
So on a slide before, if you
actually have four subclasses of a common superclass
and they're really all specialized according
to the same dimension, you could still
write a meaningful name on
this "ridge" of inheritance arrows here.
But in the concrete example, there
are actually two different kinds of generalization.
That's why there are these
two different groups with different names.
Now one
can assign properties
to these generalization groups, i.e. this
left side and the right side.
So this decomposition of all cars
into private cars and company cars
or into diesel cars and solar cars,
it doesn't have to be a real decomposition.
Perhaps it is
not exhaustive at all.
Perhaps there
are also overlaps.
So if you think about which
properties might be relevant, you end up
with a pair of opposites regarding
the exhaustion of all instances and a
pair of opposites regarding the question of
whether each instance can be uniquely assigned.
This is then
called "complete" versus "incomplete".
So here the first property would
be that a generalization group is complete
if it actually conceptually covers
all conceivable instances of the superclass.
So if every car is actually
either a company car or a private
car, and there is
not a third possibility.
Then this generalization group
would be "complete", otherwise "incomplete".
That is, if there
were also possible instances
of the superclass that are
not exhausted by the subclasses.
So that would be
even with our "drive".
If there is a third class of
possible cars besides solar car and diesel car,
then the distinction between diesel and
solar cars would not be complete.
That is the one question, the
one pair of properties, of which "complete"
or "incomplete" applies to a
concrete generalization group in each case.
Then there is this other
pair of properties: "overlapping" or "disjoint".
That is, overlapping or
disjoint from each other.
"Overlapping"
means:
Instances are conceivable that could belong to
more than one of the specialization classes.
This could be imagined in the case of the
distinction between company and private cars, if there are
also cars that are a bit
of both, i.e., mixed-financed, so to speak.
Then that distinction
would be "overlapping."
And "disjoint" would
be the opposite, namely
that these specializing classes
do not conceptually overlap.
If it is not
possible to have such mixed
financing, if a car is
always in fact exactly either fully
corporate-owned or fully privately-owned,
then this subdivision, this generalization
group, would
be called "disjoint"/"disjoint."
And of course, if we have a choice
here between "complete" and "incomplete" and a choice
here between "overlapping" and "disjoint," then there
are a total of four possible combinations:
complete-overlapping, incomplete-overlapping,
complete-disjoint, incomplete-disjoint.
We have four cases, and in fact you
can also think of constellations that actually occur
for each of
the four cases.
We can go through this for
our example from before and other examples.
So, for example, the left side of our
example distinction seen earlier, the generalization relationship between
"car" on the one
hand and "private car"/"company car"
on
the other.
So distinction
by status.
That's a generalization group and we could
consider that to be complete and disjoint.
So let's assume there's no other kind of
status that a car can have in that
respect, and we don't
allow for mixed private/corporate cars.
Then that would be a complete
and disjunctive distinction in that respect.
Then, in fact, what you end up doing
is really partitioning the instances of the upper class.
So each car falls into
exactly one of these subclasses.
Neither does it fall out of the classes, nor does
it fall into more than one class at a time.
If we take the right-hand
side of our diagram from
just now, that is, the
distinction by drive, that's also disjoint.
It's also a disjoint distinction because there
is no car that is both diesel
and solar at the same
time (I'm just assuming now, technically).
But it's not
"complete", it's incomplete, because
there are still
gasoline cars, for example.
That is another
combination of properties.
Then "complete" and
"overlapping" are still missing.
This could be imagined, for
example, not with cars and their
subclasses, but with
animals and their subclasses.
For example, if we distinguish animals by
habitat, then there are land animals, water
animals, and air
animals or flying animals.
I would say
that's a complete distinction.
So even more habitats of
animals don't exist if we limit
ourselves to planet Earth and
don't somehow add outer space.
But one could
argue that this distinction
is "overlapping," that
is, not "disjoint."
Why?
Because, for example, there are animals
that are both land and water animals.
Turtles,
for example.
They are neither clearly assigned to the land
habitat, nor clearly assigned to the water habitat.
In this respect, this would not
be an overlap-free or disjunctive distinction.
What we also see here
in the example is that
of course this distinction does not always
have to happen exactly in two subclasses.
That may have still
suggested this example here,
that we always subdivide
exactly into two subclasses.
Of course,
that's not true.
We can see
that in this example.
There can also be
more than two subclasses.
And still, one can then investigate
these properties in a meaningful way.
Then there is one more
constellation missing, namely "incomplete" and "overlapping".
And we can
get these, for example,
if we simply omit
a subclass from this diagram.
So forget that there
are also flying animals.
Then we would
be at this picture.
This is still
"overlapping", because there are
still the turtles, which would
fit into both subclasses here.
But since the flying animals are missing,
this would not be a complete distinction.
Thus all four constellations would
be occupied once by an example.